A Guide to the Lindsay West Papers, 1975-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Lindsay West Papers, 1975-1996
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
West, Lindsay Butte (1934-2018)
Ms2001-013
1.5 Linear Feet 2 boxes; 2 oversize folders
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
Lindsay Butte West (born 1934) was a member of the Montgomery County (Virginia) Board of Supervisors from 1976-1987. One of six new supervisors elected in 1976, she was the first woman elected to the Board. She was vice-chair in 1976-1977 and chair in 1979-80 and 1986-87.
Taking a particular interest in human service and environmental and land-use issues, West represented the Board of Supervisors on the Montgomery County Social Services Board, the New River Community Action Board, and the Montgomery County Public Service Authority (1982-1989; chair, 1984-1985). Shortly after she was elected, West led an unsuccessful effort to reverse the decision of the previous Board to tear down the historic Montgomery County Courthouse building in Christiansburg.
While on the Board of Supervisors, West also served on the state Local Government Advisory Council (1981-1985) and the Local Government Advisory Committee of the Governor's Commission of Transportation (1986- 1987). She was Chair of the Montgomery County Democratic Committee from 1988-1997 and has been active in a variety of other community organizations and causes in Montgomery County, including the restoration of the Lyric Theater in Blacksburg. She also served on the Montgomery-Floyd Regional Library Blacksburg Branch Building Committee in 1990. Lindsay West was born in San Juan, Puerto Rico, in 1934 and grew up in New York. She earned a B.A. from Radcliff College in 1956 and moved to Blacksburg in 1962.
Lindsay West died in 2018.
Note:
Gina Beasley, "Lindsay West: Long Live the Lyric," Western Waters, Winter 2002, 40.
Scope and Contents
The Lindsay West Papers span the years 1975-1996. The bulk of the collection is comprised of subject files West kept while she was serving on the Montgomery County Board of Supervisors in southwest Virginia. These files contain inter- and intra- office county government correspondence and memos, legal opinions, government documents, reports and studies, many of which include maps; and clippings. Most of the correspondence and documents are photocopies of county government documents distributed by the county staff to each member of the Board. The papers document Montgomery County government during a period of rapid growth and change in the New River Valley. Subjects include: annexation actions, the proposed Ingles Mountain Landfill in Radford, a proposed alternate for Route 460, and a proposal to develop a shopping mall along Route 460.
The collection also contains records documenting the following entities: New River Community Action, the New River Valley Workshop, and the Montgomery-Floyd Regional Library Board Blacksburg Library Building Committee, including a poster announcing the dedication of the new building in 1996.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged into the following series: Montgomery County Board of Supervisors (the bulk of the collection), Local Government Advisory Committee to the Commission on Transportation in the Twenty- First Century, Montgomery - Floyd Regional Library Board Blacksburg Area Branch Building Committee, New River Community Action, New River Valley Workshop, Virginia Tech Horticulture Farm Rezoning Request Review Committee, Speeches and Writings, and Personal Papers (two folders comprised primarily of clippings).
Index Terms
Persons:
West, Lindsay Butte (1934-2018)
Subjects:
Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; Montgomery County (Va.); Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Blacksburg (Va.); University Archives
Contents List
- Montgomery County Board of Supervisors, 1975-1987
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged into the following subseries: Minutes, Subject Files, and Legal Cases. It is comprised primarily of subject files.
  - Minutes, Reports, and Agendas, August-October 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    Scope and Contents
    Photocopies of agendas and minutes from Montgomery County Board of Supervisors meetings; includes copies of related correspondence and county documents pertaining to items on the meeting agendas.
  - Subject Series, 1975-1987
    This subseries is comprised of subject files kept by Lindsay West in the course of her work as a member of the Montgomery County Board of Supervisors between 1975 and 1987. The files contain photocopies of correspondence, memoranda, and documents that were distributed to members of the Board of Supervisors; reports, studies, publications, clippings, and other materials. Some of the materials include notes made by West.
    Alphabetical by subject. Oversize materials are stored in oversize folder.
    - Accounting manual, county-government, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Annexation Report, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Memo outlining legal issues raised by annexation proceedings involving Radford and Christiansburg and a possible attempt by Blacksburg to attempt to seek city status.
    - Blacksburg City Status, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
      Copies of correspondence with County Administrator Betty Thomas, data on Blacksburg schools, Montgomery County social services, a 1977 city- status study, clippings, and other documents pertaining to a possible attempt by Blacksburg to seek city status.
    - Blacksburg, Goals for, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Planning Department proposal to involve citizens in discussion of planning issues.
    - Blacksburg, Government Structures Committee, Report of, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Blacksburg, Government Structure Committee, Subcommittee on Education, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Survey and summary of findings.
    - Blacksburg in the '80s: Citizens Planning for Tomorrow, 1980-1981, 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
      Correspondence, minutes, reports, and other materials documenting a commission established by the Blacksburg Town Council to encourage citizen participation in town planning.
    - Blacksburg Library Building, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15, Oversize 1)
      Documents, correspondence, blueprint, and reports pertaining to construction of a library building for the Blacksburg branch of the Montgomery-Floyd Regional Library.
    - Capital Improvements Program Committee, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Christiansburg Land Sludge Disposal Plan, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Includes copies of the draft plan and request for approval and correspondence pertaining to the request.
    - Christiansburg-Montgomery County Settlement Agreement, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18, Oversize 1, Oversize 2)
      Materials include a Statement of Response from Ann Hess, Supervisor, District B; correspondence, clippings and maps pertaining to the agreement between Christiansburg and Montgomery County regarding annexation and implementation of systematic provision of utility service.
      - Map Exhibits, Montgomery County Annexation Proceedings, 1986 (Folder 2)
        Maps illustrating effects of proposed annexation on the provision of local government services.
      - Maps of the Town of Christiansburg and Environs showing existing land use for proposed annexation area, 1987, 7 maps (Folder 1)
    - Harman Farms/Yellow Sulphur Springs, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Documents pertaining to a request on the part of Harman Farms for an amendment to the zoning ordinance and a conditional-use permit.
    - Legal Issues (miscellaneous), 1979-1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Memos and correspondence from County Attornies Roy Thorpe and Paul Mahoney with analysis of legal issues of concern to the Board of Supervisors.
    - Montgomery County Courthouse Renovation, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 21-22, Oversize 1)
      Correspondence, documents, blueprints and drawings pertaining to the proposed renovation of the Montgomery County Courthouse.
    - Montgomery County Museum, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Documents pertaining to construction of the museum.
    - Montgomery County Public Service Authority, Agreement with the Town of Christiansburg, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Contract, agreement, and other documents pertaining to the water agreement between the Town of Christiansburg and Montgomery County.
    - Montgomery Shopping Mall, 1978, 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
      Development proposal, memo from County Administrator regarding the proposal, and a traffic-impact study.
    - "The New and Little: A River Access Study," by Edward M. DeTrude, Jr., Mike Birchner, and Tom Bain, Montgomery County Parks and Recreation Department, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - New River Resource Authority, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Clippings.
    - New River Valley Planning District, Grant to Western Virginia EMS Council, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      Report summarizing grant.
    - Radford, City of, 1984-1986
      - Montgomery County Statement and Answer to Radford City Council, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 30)
        Documents pertaining to negotiations over sewage treatment, erosion, and a proposed landfill.
      - Radford Annexation, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 31)
        Documents pertaining to the Montgomery County Annexation Case.
      - Proposed Settlement Agreement, City of Radford and Montgomery County, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Ingles Mountain Landfill (proposed), 1985-1986, 4 folders and 1 oversize map (Box 1, Folder 33-36, Folder 1)
        Reports, staff analysis, correspondence, clippings, and topographic base map showing site of the proposed Ingles Mountain Landfill.
    - Roanoke River Upper Basin Public Assistance Committee, 1978-1985, 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
      Correspondence, memoranda, clippings, and reports, including U.S. Army Corps of Engineers Plan of Study for the Roanoke River Upper Basin.
      - Planning Brochure, Roanoke River Upper Basin, Virginia Water Resources Study, 1979 (Folder 2)
        U.S. Army Corps of Engineers report; includes conceptual and topographic maps.
    - Route 460 Alternate (proposed), and Blacksburg to Roanoke Connector, 1986-1991 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
      Correspondence, clippings, studies, speeches and writings.
      - Route 460 Corridor Study, Virginia Department of Transportation, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Blacksburg to Roanoke Connector, Pre-Hearing Publication, Virginia Department of Transportation, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Solar Energy Education and Research Center, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Correspondence and staff analysis of a proposal to build a facility for manufacturing solar homes.
  - Legal Cases, 1975-1977
    - Allegheny Construction Company v. Graves Construction Company v. Montgomery County, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Peter C. Snyder v. Montgomery County Board of Supervisors, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Commission on Transportation in the Twenty-First Century, Report of the Local Government Advisory Committee to the Commission, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Report and speech notes.
- Montgomery-Floyd Regional Library Board, Blacksburg Area Branch Committee, 1969-1996 (Box 2, Folder 10-11, Oversize 1)
  Minutes, Building Program, Report on Collection/Circulation Statistics, Records documenting bond referendum, feasibility study, poster from building dedication, and map showing plot of property on Miller Street to be exchanged between the Town of Blacksburg and Charles N. Liskey.
- New River Community Action, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Report, by-laws, publications, journal of World Share visit to Celaya, Guanahuato.
- New River Valley Workshop, Inc., 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Goals and Objectives, Long-Range Planning Document, financial statements, and report on New River Valley "Idea" Conference on Creating Spin-off Industries and Jobs Using Recoverable Materials from Solid Waste.
- Virginia Tech Horticultural Farm, Re-zoning Request Review Committee, 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Personal Papers, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  Notes for remarks West made pertaining to a Democratic party meeting, the New River Community Council, and the library; and a file of photocopies of memos, correspondence, and other materials pertaining to a proposal to condemn a portion of Nellie's Cave Road.